From Idaho Capitol Sun Idaho
legislature passes bill for
Medicaid expansion work
requirements by 2027 government
plus politics Idaho legislature
passes bill for Medicaid
expansion work requirements by
2027 Adopting big beautiful bill
work requirements could cut
Idaho Medicaid expansion
enrollment by up to 44
researchers found By advocates
for Idaho Medicaid and people
with disabilities rally against
proposed federal Medicaid cuts
in front of the Idaho State
Capitol on Thursday March 20th
2025 Idaho Capitol Sun
Republicans in the Idaho
legislature widely approved
implementing federal Medicaid
work requirements for adults
enrolled in Medicaid expansion
by the end of the year House
Bill 19 calls for Idaho to adopt
Medicaid work requirements that
were part of President Donald
Trump's cornerstone law the One
Big Beautiful Bill Act The
policy could remove up to 44 of
Idahoans or 34 000 people from
Medicaid expansion researchers
say After passing the Idaho
Senate on a 28 6 party line vote
Tuesday the bill heads to
Governor Brad Little for final
consideration Need to get in
touch Have a news tip Lawmakers
pushing for the change say they
want to make sure that people
who are receiving Medicaid and
can work are working But
advocates say Medicaid work
requirements are effectively
costly administrative barriers
to access the program The rules
they say could kick working
Idahoans off the program because
many would fail to submit the
right paperwork Medicaid work
requirements and other changes
in the Big Beautiful Bill could
kick 20 000 to 34 000 Idahoans
off Medicaid expansion by 2028
according to an analysis
published last week by the Urban
Institute and the Robert Wood
Johnson Foundation Idaho
Medicaid expansion covers nearly
79 000 Idahoans About 48 of able
bodied adults on Idaho Medicaid
are working according to a
December report by the Idaho
Department of Health and Welfare
In 2018 nearly 61 of Idaho
voters approved Medicaid
expansion through a ballot
initiative meant to close a
healthcare assistance gap that
affected a population commonly
called the working poor Other
states experiences and a federal
watchdog report suggest costs
for Medicaid work requirements
are high In the legislature the
bill had support from all 87
Republican lawmakers who were
present with one exception
Grayson Stone a long term
substitute for Rep Don Hall Twin
Falls was the only Republican to
vote against the bill The 14
Democrats present for votes
opposed the bill Once the bill
is transmitted to the governor's
desk he has five days excluding
Sundays to decide on it He has
three options sign it allow it
to become law without his
signature or veto it Get the
morning headlines These work
requirements might not need
federal approval often In the
past the legislature had made
similar calls to require able
bodied adults on Medicaid
expansion to prove they are
working to receive benefits
through the public assistance
program But those rules need
approval from the federal
government which is often a
lengthy process that Idaho
hasn't succeeded with Rep John
Vander Wouda our NAMPA speaks
from the House floor at the
Idaho Capitol on April 6th 2021
photo by Otto Kitzinger for
Idaho Capitol Sun NAMPA
Republican Rep John Vander Wouda
who's sponsoring the bill hopes
the state wouldn't need federal
approval for this iteration of
work requirements In 2019 Idaho
failed to receive federal
approval then by the first Trump
administration for Medicaid work
requirements In 2025 the Idaho
legislature and the governor
approved another bill that
called for Idaho to seek federal
approval for Medicaid work
requirements Medicaid enrollees
would need to prove they are
working twice a year to maintain
coverage because the federal law
requires enrollment renewals
every six months Idaho's bill
would require state health
officials to verify work history
for Medicaid enrollees over a
period of three months The
longest look back Time allowed
under the federal law That
period is long enough to ensure
people don't just get a job
weeks before they apply to
Medicaid Sen Julie Van Orden a
Republican from Pingree said
Tuesday I feel like what we're
doing is pretty conservative she
said Senator Melissa Wintrow
DuBois listens to proceedings
during the Joint Finance
Appropriations Committee meeting
on January 14th 2026 at the
State Capitol building in Boise
Photo by Pat Sutphin for the
Idaho Capitol Sun But Boise
Democratic Senator Melissa
Wintrow said compared using the
longest look back period allowed
to adding red tape to kick more
people off Medicaid expansion
This bill is an attempt to do a
backdoor repeal of Medicaid
expansion Wintrow said Vander
Woude called for a staggered
implementation of the work rules
The Department of Health and
Welfare could do an early review
later this year before the work
requirements officially take
effect in January Vander Woude
says that would give people time
to fix their work status to
remain on the program In a
statement Tuesday the American
Cancer Society Cancer Action
Network asked the governor to
veto the bill Forcing these
people into a suffocating
paperwork quagmire will serve no
function other than to keep them
and their children from getting
the care they need be it cancer
treatment a mammogram or a
regular checkup the group's
Idaho Government Relations
Director Randy Johnson said What
would the Medicaid work
requirements look like The bill
calls for Idaho to adopt by
December 31st 2026 Medicaid work
requirements included in the One
Big Beautiful Bill Act The
federal law requires the work
requirements to take effect by
2027 The federal law's work
requirements will require that
people enrolled in Medicaid
expansion work or do community
service at least 80 hours per
month according to health policy
research group KFF Several
exemptions would apply such as
for people who are enrolled in
school at least half time
caretakers or parents of
dependent children younger than
13 years old or people with
disabilities pregnant or
receiving postpartum coverage
veterans with disabilities and
those under age 26 who are or
were in foster care The Idaho
bill would require that people
comply with the work
requirements for three months
before they apply to Medicaid
The Idaho Department of Health
and Welfare would remove any
person who is unable to
demonstrate compliance from
Medicaid If passed into law the
bill would take effect
immediately You make our work
possible Kyle Fanenstiel is a
reporter for the Idaho Capitol
Sun covering healthcare and
state politics He previously
reported for the Post Register
Report for America Idaho
Education News and the Idaho
Press Kyle is a military brat
who calls Idaho home He has a
bachelor's degree in journalism
and political science from
University of Idaho Idaho
Capitol Sun is part of States
Newsroom the nation's largest
state focused nonprofit news
organization